hello大家好我是凯超
Hello everyone, I am Kaichao
我们今天课程的内容是Substrate Runtime宏的介绍
The content of our course today is about Substrate Runtime macros.
今天课程内容主要包含
Today's course mainly includes
Rust宏的基本介绍
A quick introduction to Rust macros
以及使用Substrate进行Runtime进行开发的时候经常使用的宏
And the macros defined in Substrate for runtime development
接着我们会介绍使用cargo-expand工具来将这样的宏展开
Next we will introduce the cargo-expand tool to expand such macros
最后我们会看一下Substrate提供的一些其他帮助性的宏
Finally we will take a look at some of other useful macros in Substrate.
宏是一种元编程的方式
Macros are a form of metaprogramming
那类似的概念在Java里面称作反射
the similar concept is called reflection in Java
在Rust编程语言里提供了两种宏的语法
There are two kinds of macro syntax in Rust
一种是声明宏一种是过程宏
One is declarative macro and the other is procedural macro
这里我给出了一个链接
here's a link of Rust doc which describes some basic knowledge of macros in Rust
里面描述了Rust宏的一些基本的知识和常用的介绍
Substrate使用宏的原因是为了简化区块链Runtime的开发
The reason Substrate uses macros is to simplify the development of blockchain runtime
稍后我们会介绍一下什么是Runtime
Later we will introduce what is Runtime
通过使用宏可以建立一套自定义的DSL
A custom DSL (aka, Domain Specific Language) can be built by using macros
也就是领域特定语言
那一个合理的领域特定语言可以很好的被用户所理解
A well designed  DSL can be understood by users easily.
在这里的话就是区块链的开发者
In our case, the users of Substrate are blockchain developers
那同样的使用这样的DSL
By using the DSL provided by Substrate, it can make code development more concise and efficient
可以让我们的代码开发变得更加简洁
效率也更加高
By using the DSL provided by Substrate, it can make code development more concise and efficient
从而能够让区块链应用开发者
therefore blockchain developers don't need to care about the underlying databases, p2p network, cryptography and WASM execution environment, etc.
不需要去关心底层的这些数据库, 点对点网络, 密码学和WASM执行环境这些公共的底层组件
只需要使用DSL编写上层的应用业务组件就可以了
they only need to code the business compoments on the application layer.
接着我们来看一下Substrate Runtime的定义
Then let's take a look at the definition of Substrate Runtime
大家应该已经知道
you should already know that
区块链里区块的验证是通过链上的逻辑进行校验的
the verification of the blocks in blockchain is through some onchain logic
那在Substrate里面
In Substrate, such onchain logic is called Runtime
对应的链上逻辑我们称之为Runtime
区块链的链上状态A转换到新的链上状态B
State transition from onchain state A to onchain state B is triggered by transactions
需要通过交易进行触发
将对应的交易信息应用到我们的Runtime逻辑层
apply the transactions to the Runtime logic
进行状态的修改
thus changes the onchain state
那在Substrates内置了很多Runtime的功能模块
Substrate provides a lot of build-in modules which can be used in runtime
这些功能模块也被称之为pallet
such modules are also called pallets
常用的有资产管理相关的assets, balance
Commonly used modules includes assets management features like assets, balances pallets
共识相关的babe, grandpa
consensus related pallets like babe, grandpa
以及治理相关的collective, democracy, elections, sudo
governance related pallets like collective, democracy, elections, sudo, etc.
还有权益证明相关的staking
and Proof of Staking related pallets like staking.
以及智能合约contract
also the smart contract pallet called contracts
这些模块都是可组合的可自由添加
All of these pallets are composable and can be used freely
根据你链上逻辑的要求可以自由的进行选择
you only need to choose the ones that fit for your business
但是这些模块都要依赖于一个公共的系统模块
Most of the pallets depend on the frame-system pallet
叫做system
在使用Substrate进行Runtime功能模块开发的时候
When developing a module for Substrate Runtime
我们经常使用到下面这些宏
We often use the following macros
第一个是frame_support::pallet
The first is frame_support::pallet
可以用来我们定义一个新的功能模块
it can be used to define a new module
接着是使用pallet::config来定义我们功能模块所需要的配置接口
Then use pallet::config to define the configuration trait of our module
The configuration trait usually contains some dependent data and associate types.
配置接口里面通常会包含一些
依赖的数据信息和类型信息
The configuration trait usually contains some dependent data and associate types.
pallet::storage可以定义
pallet::storage macro can be used to define the onchain storage items
我们所需要的链上存储单元
pallet::event定义链上可以触发的事件
pallet::event defines the events that can be triggered on chain
pallet::error定义了链上交易可以接受的错误信息
pallet::error defines the error types that caused by sending transactions
pallet::call定义了我们链上的可调用函数
pallet::call defines the dipatchable functions
也就是对应的我们不同的交易类型
corresponding to our different transaction types
pallet::hooks定义了一些独特的函数
pallet::hooks defines some unique functions that can be executed at different periods of a block
可以在区块的不同时期进行执行
consruct_runtime用来把我们新添加的功能模块加入到Runtime里
Macro consruct_runtime is used to add our new module into the Runtime
不管是传统的互联网应用还是以区块链技术为代表的Web3.0应用
Whether it's traditional Web2.0 applications or blockchain based Web3.0 applications
那关键性的数据都需要进行存储
the critical data needs to be stored, so that it can be processed and used later
从而可以被后续进行处理和使用
Substrate的storage宏就是用来定义链上的存储单元
Substrate's storage macro is used to define onchain storage items.
这里我们看一个storage宏的例子
Here let's look at an example of storage macro
在解释storage宏之前我们首先来看我们之前提到几个宏
before explaining the storage macro, let's first look at several others macros we mentioned before
一个是frame_support::pallet
One is frame_support::pallet, which is used to define our new module
用来定义我们一个新的功能模块
我们这里名字叫做pallet
here the module is called pallet
功能模块的名字叫做pallet
接着我们是使用pallet::config来定义我们功能模块的配置接口
Then we use pallet::config to define the configuration trait of our module
这里我们定义了一个配置接口
here we define a configuration trait called config
名字是config
它继承自system模块config接口
it inherits from the config trait of system module
我们刚才已经提到了
we just mentioned that
每个功能模块都要继承自我们的系统模块
each runtime module should inherits from our system module
我们当前的功能模块儿配置接口里面
The config trait of our module has a associate type called RuntimeEvent
有个关联类型是RuntimeEvent
这个event有两个类型约束
There are two type constraints applied to RuntimeEvent
一个是它可以从
one is that it can be converted from the module's event
自己模块的event进行转换
并且它是系统模块
the other is that it conforms to the event type in system module
event这样的一个类型
接着我们就可以看storage存储宏
Now let's look at the stroage macro
我们是使用pallet::storage这样的一个宏
we are using the macro syntax #[pallet::storage]
待会我们再来看getter这个宏
later we'll introduce pallet::getter macro
这里我们定义了一个类型别名something
for storage macro, here it defines a type alias called Something
它真实类型是StorageValue
which alias to the real type StorageValue
它有两个泛型参数第一个是下划线
it has two generic parameters, the first is underscore, the second is u32
第二个是U32表示
u32表示我们真实的Something
here u32 means the storage item Something can store a 32 bits integer
这样一个存储单元
所能存储的数据类型
here u32 means the storage item Something can store a 32 bits integer
也就是32位的整数类型
第一个下划线泛型参数
the first underscore means there is a default prefix for the storage item
表示的是我们存储单元
对应的一个prefix
the first underscore means there is a prefix for the storage item
通常情况下我们用下划线进行表示
we use underscore to represent the default prefix implementation
当我们需要去修改
modify the underscore to a new prefix implementation if you want to change the default behavior
存储单元的prefix时候才需要去
才需要去重新定义
modify the underscore to a new prefix implementation if you want to change the default behavior
那pallet::getter宏的话
Now let's see pallet::getter macro
是定义一个可选的get函数
it defines an optional get function for the storage item
这里它的get函数是something
here the get function is named something
这样我们可以很方便的使用这个get函数来获取对应的存储单元里面的内容
we can easily use this get function to retrieve the value stored in the storage item
另外一个点是我们
Another point is that we
定义存储单元的时候
When defining a storage unit
这个泛型T是不可缺省的
This generic T is indispensable
它和
it and
标准的Rust语法可能稍微有些不一样
Standard Rust syntax may be slightly different
那除了我们刚才看到的StorageValue
So in addition to the StorageValue we just saw
这样的一个
such a
存储的数据类型之外
Stored data types other than
还可以有其他的存储类型
There can also be other storage types
StorageValue是用来存储单个数值
StorageValue is used to store a single value
另外的两个是一个是存出映射类型
The other two are one is to store out the mapping type
也就是一个key-value的键值对
That is, a key-value key-value pair
它的类型StorageMap
It is of type StorageMap
还有一个是双键映射类型
There is also a double key value type
就是有两个键对应一个值
There are two keys corresponding to a value
它的类型是StorageDoubleMap
Its type is StorageDoubleMap
在后面的课程
in later courses
我们会详细的介绍不同
We will introduce the different
的数据存储类型
type of data storage
还有一个键值的类型叫做StorageNMap
There is also a key-value type called StorageNMap
用来把多个键对应一个值的
Used to map multiple keys to a single value
map数据类型
map data type
比如可以有3个键或者4个键
For example, there can be 3 keys or 4 keys
他们来共同对应一个值
They come together to correspond to a value
这里我们也给出了文档链接
Here we also give the documentation link
希望大家可以看一看
I hope you can take a look
接着我们来看一下
Let's take a look
Substrate的call这样的一个宏
A macro like Substrate's call
大家知道
Everybody knows
区块链的链上状态
On-chain state of the blockchain
通常都是由交易进行触发的
Usually triggered by a transaction
那在Substrate里面不仅支持一些简单的
Then in Substrate it not only supports some simple
交易比如转账这样的简单交易
Transactions Simple transactions such as transfers
还可以支持自定义的一些交易类型
It can also support some custom transaction types
比如注册链上的身份
For example, you can register an identity on the chain
你可以进行治理相关的投票
You can vote on governance
在Substrate的里面
Inside the Substrate
这样的交易通常叫做extrinsic
Such transactions are usually called extrinsic
表示外部交易
Indicates external transactions
是由外部用户来触发的
is triggered by an external user
每一个外部交易
every external transaction
都会对应一个可调用函数
will correspond to an adjustable function
那可调用函数就是通过call
The adjustable function is through call
这样的一个宏
such a macro
在模块里面进行定义的
defined in the module
可调用函数会根据我们的函数参数
The adjustable function will be based on our function parameters
进行我们自定义逻辑的处理
to perform our own logic processing
来对列上状态进行更新
To update the state on the column
这里我们看一个call的例子
Here we look at an example of a call
在之前
before
我们已经定义了一个pallet
We have defined a pallet
这样的一个结构体
such a structure
表示我们
showing us
功能模块
the functional module
接着我们对pallet
Then in the pallet struct
结构体添加了一些功能实现
we add some functional implementation
在这个功能实现
Outside the implementation
外面我们
we use
应用了pallet::call这样的一个宏来表示
a macro such as pallet::call to represent that
这个实现里面是我们的可调用函数
Inside this implementation is our callable function
对应的是不同的交易
Corresponding to different transactions
这里面
here
其中一个可调用函数的名字是do_something
The name of one of the callable functions is do_something
它接受两个参数
It accepts two parameters
第一个参数是origin
The first parameter is origin
表示交易的发送方
which Indicates the sender of the transaction
它的类型是OriginFor
Its type is OriginFor
来自我们的系统模块
from our system modules
另外一个数据是something
Another data is something
它是32位整数类型
It is a 32-bit integer type
返回结果是DispatchResult
The return result is DispatchResult
是一个Rust Result类型的类型别名
It is a type alias for the Rust result type
包含了Substrates所返回的一些
which contains some of the
自定义的错误信息
custom error messages
pallet::weight这个宏我们稍后再去介绍
The macro pallet::weight will be introduced later
call_index宏
call_index macro
可以把可调用函数在codec
can fix the sequence
callable functions in code
编解码过程中的顺序
in the encoding and decoding process
固定下来
比如do something
such as do something
它的序号是0
its serial number is 0
在这个可调用函数里面它的逻辑很简单
Inside this callable function its logic is simple
首先是使用系统文化提供的ensure_signed
The first is to use the ensure_signed provided by the system culture
将origin进行较验
to verify the origin
看对应的交易发送方是不是
See if the corresponding transaction sender is
经过签名的
signed
如果是签名的话我们返回我
If it's signed it returns
们交易的发送方对应的account
the account corresponding to the sender of our transaction
接着我们交易完成之后
Then after our transaction is completed
我们就可以对我们存储单元进行
We can then modify
修改我们将something
our storage unit
刚才提到的something这样一个存储单元
The something just mentioned such a storage unit
里面存储值进行更新
The value stored inside is updated
是使用put函数
It is to use the put function
紧接着
Immediately after
我们就可以触发一个事件来表示
we can trigger an event to indicate
来告诉客户端我们的
to tell the client our
逻辑执行成功了
logic execution succeeded
我们触发的事件是SomethingStored
The event we trigger is SomethingStored
这样的一个事件
such an event
它有两个数据
it has two data
一个是something
one is something
表示我们更新的数据信息
Indicating our updated data information
以及who
and who
表示我们是谁来更新的这样的信息
Indicating who we are to update such information
最后我们就可以返回OK
Finally we can return OK
那pallet::weight宏的话是表示我们
The pallet::weight macro means that
当前交易或者说是可调用函数do_something
The current transaction or callable do_something
所需要的执行的时间
required execution time
大家知道对于区块链应用
Everyone knows that for blockchain applications
区块的生成时间通常都是有限的
Block generation time is usually limited
通常是几秒钟
usually a few seconds
那在有限的区块生成时间里
that in the limited block generation time
we need to make a reasonable allocation
我们就需要对这个时间
进行合理的分配
to the time.
对应的分配的机制就是通过
The corresponding allocation mechanism is through
量化
Quantify
某一个可调用函数的执行时间来完成的
the execution time of a callable function to complete
而量化的方式就是pallet::weight交易权重
The quantification method is pallet::weight transaction weight
来进行一个设置
to make a setting
设置一个合理的权重值
Set a reasonable weight value
也就是表示这个
That is to say this
可调用函数的一个合理的执行时间
A reasonable execution time for callable functions
进而将对应的权重值转换为交易费用
Then convert the corresponding weight value into a transaction fee
通过交易费用这种机制
Through the transaction fee mechanism
来更好的避免拒绝服务类似的攻击
To better avoid attacks like denial of service
我们接着来再看一个
let's see one more
另外一个可调用函数是cause_error
Another callable function is cause_error
同样它有一个weight值
Also it has a weight value
那这里都是为了方便起见
it's all here for convenience
给它一个固定的值
to give it a fixed value
通常情况下
usually
不同的可调用函数它有不同逻辑
Different callable functions have different logic
它的权重的计算也是会和
Its weight calculation will also be relevant with
逻辑里面所读取
the specific information
去操作存储单元的
reading in logic
具体信息会有关系
to operate the storage unit.
我们本次课程并不会详细的介绍
We will not introduce in detail in this course
如何设置交易权重
about how to set trade weight
在后续的进阶课程
In subsequent advanced courses
我们会有更多的一些介绍
We will have some more introductions
这里我们定义一个另外可调用函数叫做
Here we define an additional callable function called
casue_error它只有一个参数就是origin
Casue_error has only one parameter which is origin
表示我们交易的发送方
Indicating the sender of our transaction
同样它也返回一个类型叫做DispatchResult
It also returns a type called DispatchResult
我们也是使用ensure_signed
We also use ensure_signed
来表示我们的交易
to represent that our transaction
发送方是一个签名的
sender is signed
接着我们调用get方法
Then we call the get method
获取存储单元something
to get storage unit something
里面的值
the value inside
检查里面的值是不是None
Check if the value inside is None
如果是None的话我们就返回一个error
If it is None we return an error
是NoneValue
is NoneValue
如果是有值的话
if it has a value
我们就对里面的值进行加1
We add 1 to the corresponding value inside
那加1的
that plus 1
结果如果是溢出的话
If the result is an overflow
我们就返回另外一个错误
we return another error
叫StorageOverflow
Called StorageOverflow
如果是正常情况下
if it is normal
我们就把对应加1之后的值进行存储
We store the corresponding value after adding 1
我们是调用的是put方法
We are calling the put method
最后我们返回我们所需要的
Finally we return what we need
OK数据类型
OK data type
看完了call
finished calling
这样的一个宏之后我们来看event宏
After such a macro, let's look at the event macro
大家知道区块链是一个异步系统
Everyone knows that blockchain is an asynchronous system
Substrate链上逻辑通过触发事件的形式
The logic on the Substrate chain is in the form of triggering events
来通知客户端交易的执行结果
To notify the client of the execution result of the transaction
这里事件
here event
的定义就是要使用pallet::event
The definition is to use pallet::event
这样的一个宏
such a macro
这里我们定义了一个枚举类型
Here we define an enum type
enum Event
它有一个泛型参数T
It has a generic parameter T
约束是我们当前模块化的config配置接口
Constraints is our current modular config configuration trait
给我们定义了一个
It defines an
事件类型是SomethingStored
event type which is SomethingStored
第一个参数是U32 表示我们操作的数据
The first parameter is U32 representing the data we operate
第二个参数是T::AccountId
The second parameter is T::AccountId
是系统模块所提供的类型
which is the type provided by the system module
表示我们的交易用户
Representing our trading users
另外一个是generate_deposit这样的一个宏
The other is a macro like generate_deposit
它定义了一个帮助方法deposit_event
It defines a helper method deposit_event
可以方便的来触发事件
It is convenient to trigger events
可以看到
We can see
这里我们是调用模块Self::deposit_event
Here we are calling the module Self::deposit_event
也就是我们刚才generate_deposit event
That is, we just used generate_deposit event
定义一个帮助方法
to define a helper method
来触发对应的事件
to trigger the corresponding event
我们这里的事件是
Our events here is
Event枚举类型,子类型SomethingStored
Event enumeration type, subtype SomethingStored
它有两个数据, 一个是这个数据something
It has two data one is this data something
另外一个是交易的发送者who
The other is the sender who of the transaction
当可调用函数
when any error
of the callable function occurs during execution
在执行过程中发生任何错误时
我们可以通过error信息来通知客户端
We can notify the client through error information
那需要使用的就是pallet::error这样的一个宏
Then you need to use the pallet
error macro
同样呢我们定义了一个enum Error
Similarly, we defined an enum Error
这样的一个枚举类型
Such an enumerated type
那这里我们有两个变体
So here we have two variants
一个是NoneValue表示没有值
One is NoneValue means no value
另外一个变体是StorageOverflow
Another variant is StorageOverflow
表示了存储在计算的过程中
indicating storage overflow happend
发生了溢出
in the process of calculation
通常情况下错误信息要有比较好的可读性
In general, error messages should be more readable
并且我们这里的Rust的注释文档
And our Rust annotation documentation here
也会通过metadata
Also through metadata
来暴露给客户端
to be exposed to the client
对于可调用函数里面触发的错误类型
For the error type triggered in the callable function
他们和event有一些不一样
They are a little different from event
event可以添加数据
event can add data
但是错误信息不能添加数据
But the error message cannot add data
我们刚才已经提到了
we just mentioned
错误信息也会通过metadata
Error information will also use metadata
暴露给客户端
to be exposed to clients
那当错误真正发生时
when the error actually occurs
其实是触发了一个system
In fact, it triggered a system
ExtrinsicFailed的这样一个事件
Such an event of ExtrinsicFailed
那这个事件里面就包含了对应错误的
Then this event contains the corresponding error
索引信息
index information
比如它是由哪个模块触发的
For example, which module triggers it
以及它触发的错误的index
And the index of the error it triggered
也就是错误的名字并不会真正的返回
That is, the wrong name does not really return
而是
but
具体在枚举定义的一个排序的顺序
A sorted order specifically defined in the enumeration
会返回给客户端
will be returned to the client
接着我们来看一下hooks宏
Then let's take a look at the hooks macro
在Substarte Runtime里有一些保留的函数
There are some reserved functions in Substarte Runtime
可以用在特定的时间点
can be used at a specific point in time
执行一些自定义的逻辑
to execute some custom logic
比如on_initialize这样一个保留函数
For example, a reserved function such as on_initialize
它可以在每个区块的开头进行执行
It can be executed at the beginning of each block
另外一个是on_finalize
The other one is on_finalize
他会在每个区块结束时执行
It will be execute at the end of each block
还有一个是offchain_worker
Another one is offchain_worker
它也是在区块开头的时候就会执行
It is also executed at the beginning of the block
但是不同的是它会起一个新的线程
But the difference is that it will start a new thread
并不会占用链上的执行资源
it does not occupy execution resources on the chain
通常offchain_worker可以用来
Usually offchain_worker can be used
执行一些计算量要求比较高
Performing some calculations that are relatively demanding
或者与链外系统进行交互的一些操作
Or some operations that interact with off-chain systems
比如去获取一些链外的价格信息
For example, to obtain some off-chain price information
或者身份信息等等
or identity information, etc.
那on_runtime_upgrade的话
Then on_runtime_upgrade
是当有runtime升级的时候才会执行
It will be executed when there is a runtime upgrade
通常是用做遗留数据的数据迁移功能
Usually used as a data migration function for legacy data
最后一个用来开发Runtime功能模块的
The last one is used to develop the Runtime function module
宏是construct_runtime
The macro is construct_runtime
它可以用来加载我们的
It can be used to load our
刚刚开发出来的功能模块
Functional modules just developed
在加载之前呢
before loading
首先我们要对我们的功能模块
First we have to implement our function module
配置接口进行实现
configuration trait
比如刚才我们看到的template的模块
For example, the template module we saw just now
我们对它的config配置接口进行实现
We inplement its config configuration trait
它只有一个关键类型是event
It has only one key type which is event
这里我们给它进行定义
Here we define it
接着我们就可以在construct_runtime宏里面
Then we can in the construct_runtime macro
添加我们对应的功能模块
Add our corresponding function module
这里我们功能模块的名字叫做
Here the name of our function module is called
TemplateModule
那我们需要依赖的
then we need to rely on
pallet_template模块里的一些
Something in the pallet_template module
数据信息包括
like Data informations that include
模块定义module, 可调用函数定义call
Module definition module, callable function definition call
存储项的定义storage以及event的定义
The definition of storage item storage and the definition of event
现在我们就已经完成了一个基本的
We have now completed a basic
功能模块
functional module
用来存储一个简单的值
that is used to store a simple value
如果大家对
if everyone is
Substrate的内置的宏感兴趣的话
interested in Substrate's built-in macros
可以使用cargo expend的这个工具
You can use this tool from cargo expend
将我们宏所应用的代码进行展开
to expand the code applied by our macro
能够看到更加标准化的Rust语法
and you will be able to see more standardized Rust syntax
从而也可以看到宏里面所
So you can also see what is inside the macro
生成的一些新的函数
like some new functions generated
一些帮助性的函数
some helper functions
另外大家可以去参考
In addition, you can refer to
pallet属性宏对应的文档
documentation corresponding to the pallet property macro
里面有一些详细的描述信息和
There are some detailed description information and
一些使用的例子
some usage examples
还有一些其他的宏
and some other macros
在开发Runtime模块的时候
When developing the Runtime module
有可能也会遇到
you may also use them
第一类是decl_runtime_apis和impl_runtime_apis
The first category is decl_runtime_apis and impl_runtime_apis
用来定义Runtime API
that is used to define the Runtime API
也就是可以通过
that is, through
RPC被客户端进行调用
RPC is called by the client
对链上的一些存储项进行转换
to convert some storage items on the chain
然后返回一些特定的结果给我们的
and then return some specific result to our
客户端
client
另外一类宏是runtime_interface
Another type of macro is runtime_interface
它可以定义Runtime里
It can define
可以调用的Host所提供的函数
functions provided by Host that can be called in Runtime
那大家知道Substrate
Then everyone knows Substrate
的Runtime是以wasm字节码
Runtime is stored as
形式进行存储的
wasm bytecode
那这个wasm字节码执行的话
If the wasm bytecode is executed
是需要依赖一些
is to rely on some
外部的环境
external environment
也就是我们这里的host
That is our host here
那当我们需要自定义一些
Then when we need some customized
host的方法供wasm来调用的时候
host methods is called by wasm
我们就需要用到runtime_interface
We need to use runtime_interface
这样一个宏
Such a macro
但是这样的一个宏所修改的
But such a macro modifies
信息
information
一定要在Substrate里面进行讨论和更新
needed to be sure to be discussed and updated inside Substrate
不然的话
otherwise
你编写出来的Substrate链
The Substrate chain you wrote
有可能是没有办法
there may be no way
接入到Polkadot的跨链网络里面
to be accessed to Polkadot's cross-chain network
今天课程的内容到这里就结束了
This is the end of today's lesson
谢谢大家
thank you all